<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="alpha_modifier_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2023 Xaver Hugl

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="surface alpha modifier">
    This interface allows a client to set a factor for the alpha values on a
    surface, which can be used to offload such operations to the compositor,
    which can in turn for example offload them to KMS.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
    only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="wp_alpha_modifier_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="surface alpha modifier manager">
      This interface allows a client to set a factor for the alpha values on
      a surface, which can be used to offload such operations to the
      compositor. The default factor is UINT32_MAX.

      This interface can be used to set an arbitrary alpha value for the
      surface, allowing it to be made fully transparent by setting the factor
      to 0, fully opaque by setting it to UINT32_MAX, or any value in
      between.

      Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the
      testing phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with
      the corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes
      can only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the alpha modifier manager object">
        Destroy the alpha modifier manager. This doesn't destroy objects
        created with the manager.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_surface">
      <description summary="create a new alpha modifier surface object">
        Create a new alpha modifier surface object associated with the given
        wl_surface. If there is already such an object associated with the
        wl_surface, the already_constructed error will be raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_alpha_modifier_surface_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="already_constructed" value="0"
             summary="wl_surface already has a alpha modifier object associated"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_alpha_modifier_surface_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="modifier object for a surface">
      This interface allows the client to set a factor for the alpha values on
      a surface, which can be used to offload such operations to the
      compositor. Multiple alpha modifiers can be attached to the same
      surface, in which case the resulting alpha will be the product of all
      the multiplicative factors.

      The default factor is UINT32_MAX.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="remove the alpha modifier from the surface">
        This destroys the object, and is equivalent to set_multiplier with
        a value of UINT32_MAX, with the same double-buffered semantics as
        set_multiplier.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_multiplier">
      <description summary="set the alpha multiplier">
        Sets the alpha multiplier for the surface. The alpha multiplier is
        double-buffered state, see wl_surface.commit for details.

        The default factor is UINT32_MAX.

        This factor is applied in the compositor's blending space, as an
        additional step after the processing of per-pixel alpha values for
        the surface. It allows to set an arbitrary alpha value for the
        surface, including making the surface partially transparent even when
        all the pixels are fully opaque, or fully transparent even when the
        pixels are not.
      </description>
      <arg name="factor" type="uint" summary="the new alpha multiplier for the surface"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="no_surface" value="0"
             summary="wl_surface was destroyed"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
